PARIKSHIT SUNIL DESHMUKH

pdeshmuk@buffalo.edu; Phone: +1 716 598 4517

[IN] https://www.linkedin.com/in/parikshitd92; [Git] https://github.com/parikshitdeshmukh

SUMMARY

Software Developer (ORACLE Certified JAVA Professional) with 3 years and 6 months of experience in all phases of software development with Agile Methodology. Proficient at development in Java/ J2EE, SQL, REST API, JavaScript, Python and multiple technologies including Maven, Git, Machine Learning (TensorFlow, Keras, Deep Learning), Data Mining and Data Analysis.

EDUCATION

University at Buffalo, State University of New York

• MS in Computer Science & Engineering

GPA: 3.6/4.0 Courses: Analysis of Algorithms, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Computer Security, Data Intensive Computing (Big Data)

Nagpur University, India

July 2009 - Aug 2013

Aug 2017-Feb 2019

Bachelors of Engineering

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages JAVA (Oracle Certified JAVA Professional 7), MySQL, Python, TensorFLow, R

Databases MySQL, Hibernate ORM, MS SQL Server, PostgreSQL, PL/SQL, JDBC, Amazon Web Services S3 and EC2 (cloud)

Web BootStrap, JavaScript, JQuery, REST Web Services API, HTML, CSS, PHP

Tools Git, Maven, Intellij Idea, Eclipse, Docker, R Studio, Pycharm, PGAdmin, Visual studio

OS Unix, Linux, Mac OS

Other IBM WebSphere Application Server, Machine Learning, Data Mining, JIRA, Scrum, Agile

WORK EXPERIENCE (Software Developer)

Cognizant Technology Solutions

Jan 2014 - Oct 2016

- Architected and developed insurance applications for Liberty Mutual Insurance, USA in JAVA, Struts2 MVC, JavaScript and MySQL for integrating and managing the insured and potential customers' data in MySQL database. Used and configured IBM websphere application server for managing JDBC connections and thread pool.
- Wrote complex SQL queries for performing various CRUD operations, And, functions and procedures in PL/SQL for integrating applications with databases like MySQL,DB2, MS SQL Server using JDBC API. Wrote entity-wise POJO classes.
- Utilized JavaScript and JQuery for validating the input given to the user interface and JUnit for testing functionalities of module
- Consumed and wrote RESTful web-services API using JAX-RS (Jersy) for providing the data to Underwriting vendors
- In-depth Knowledge of Core Java focusing on concepts like Multithreading, Exception Handling, File handling, I/O, Generics, Data structures, Collections, Garbage Collection with strong OO fundamentals.
- Automated Geographic refresh monthly process and optimized the PL/SQL procedure's run time by 20%
- Migrated the huddle meeting's task tracker board from Ms Excel to web-application which saved 30-40 % time for huddle meetings
- Followed Agile Methodology and used JIRA as Scrum management tool. Supervised a team of 3 new hires.
- Remedy Ticket Classification (Python, Multinomial Bayesian Network, TF-IDF): Built a Python module for a remedy system to intuitively classify the issue tickets raised by the users and allocate it to the respective operator handling that particular category of issues, which reduced manual efforts by 30-40%.

The Advisory Board Company

Oct 2016 - Jun 2017

- Designed algorithms and configurations in JAVA for processing the member (patients) data based on the business requirement and loading it into PostgreSQL database; And, also feeding it to the front end for Care Managers to manage the patient's data
- Automated the process of Quality Assurance Workbook generation by processing the incoming data, filtering it and populating the QA excel workbook, and sending mail with summary to the business analysts (+40% efficient) using Maven, JAVA and SQL

PROJECTS

- Knowledge Transition for new employee (JAVA, Bootstrap): Architected and developed a module in STRUTS2 and Bootstrap framework for on-boarding of the new employees in project which reduced human efforts by 40-50%.
- Social network Application (JAVA, REST API): Developed a small scale social networking application using RESTful web services API with JAX-RS using Jersey
- Secret Santa2 using Javascript for assigning secret santa among two people; To Do list web application using Javascript and html; Wiki on the go: wikipedia cloned version with runtime search feature.
- Predicting Airlines delay and the best airport to fly out from (Python, AWS S3):
 - performed EDA and built predictive models on the pickled datasets using Naive Bayes classifier and Logistic Regression on top of Gaussian Basis functions and validated using Early Stopping method
- Learning to rank on query-URL pair for Information Retrieval (Python):
 - Performed predictive analysis on Microsoft LETOR 4.0 dataset using Closed form solution and Stochastic Gradient Descent algorithms to gain the minimum RMSE of 0.5.
 - Incorporated Gaussian Basis function to deal with nonlinear data and, Early Stopping for the most optimal solution.
- Digit classification (Python, CNN, Tensorflow): Built and trained a logistic regression and CNN model for classifying handwritten digits and achieved accuracy of 99% using CNN model.
- Messenger (Python): Developed a web-based messaging application using Python and Flask; deployed on Docker.